<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>MALF on MALF</title>
    <link>https://maluque.netlify.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content in MALF on MALF</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Miguel Angel Luque Fernandez</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>HETMOR</title>
      <link>https://maluque.netlify.com/project/hetmor/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maluque.netlify.com/project/hetmor/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;American Journal of Public Health&lt;/strong&gt; series &amp;ldquo;Evaluating Public Health Interventions&amp;rdquo; offers excellent practical guidance to researchers in public health.  In the 8&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; part of the series, a valuable introduction to effect estimation of time-invariant public health interventions was given.[1] The authors of this article suggested that in terms of bias and efficiency there is no advantage of using modern causal inference methods over classical multivariable regression modeling.[1] However, this statement is not always true. Most importantly, both &lt;strong&gt;“effect modification”&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;“collapsibility”&lt;/strong&gt; are important concepts when assessing the validity of using regression for causal effect estimation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cancer epidemiology example&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To discuss these concepts, we are looking at an example from cancer epidemiology. In this example, we are interested in the effect of dual treatment therapy (radio- and chemotherapy), compared to single therapy (chemotherapy only) on the probability of one-year survival among colorectal cancer patients. We know that there are confounders which affect both treatment assignment and the outcome, namely clinical stage, socioeconomic status, comorbidities, and age. Evidence shows that older patients with comorbidities have a lower probability of being offered more aggressive treatments and therefore they usually get less effective curative options. Also, colorectal cancer patients from lower socioeconomic status have a higher probability of presenting an advanced clinical stage at diagnosis, thus they usually get offered only palliative treatments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Our structural assumptions in the cancer epidemiology example&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The assumptions from above can be encoded in a directed acyclic graph (DAG) (Figure 1). Here, each circle represents a variable and an arrow from A to B (A -&amp;gt; B) means that we assume that A causes B. The combination of these structural assumptions and appropriate statistical methods allow us to estimate the causal effect of dual therapy versus monotherapy on colorectal cancer patients&amp;rsquo; survival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 1&lt;/strong&gt; Directed Acyclic Graph&lt;br /&gt;
image_preview = &amp;ldquo;Figure1.png&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The question we want to answer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A clinician may be interested in the following:&lt;br /&gt;
how different would the risk of death have been had everyone received dual therapy compared to if everyone had experienced monotherapy? The causal marginal odds ratio (MOR) answers this question. Statisticians call this a “target quantity”. Each individual has a pair of potential outcomes: the outcome they would have received had they been exposed to dual treatment (A=1), denoted Y(1), and the outcome had they been unexposed, Y(0). The MOR is defined as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;image_preview = &amp;ldquo;MOR2.png&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A common approach would be to use logistic regression to model the odds of mortality given the intervention, and adjust for the confounders (W) which are age (w1)  socioeconomic status (w2), clinical stage (w3) and comorbidities (w4). Note that using a logistic regression, it estimates the conditional odds ratio (COR), which is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;COR2.png&#34; alt=&#34;Figure Link&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MOR and COR are typically not identical. First, if there is effect modification, e.g. if the effect of dual therapy is different for patients with no comorbidities compared to those having hypertension, then logistic regression (possibly including an interaction of treatment with one of the confounders) will not provide a marginal effect estimate, but only one conditional on the respective morbidity. To be more precise: we obtain an odds ratio that is valid for a given group of people, say those with hypertension, but it will not give us a marginal estimate. However, we are interested in a marginal estimate because we want to know if the dual therapy works in general. Of course, one may be specifically interested in patients with hypertension, but then the OR for this group is again conditional on the other variables, for example for elderly people, from a low socio-economic level, and advanced stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, the odds ratio is non-collapsible which means that the MOR is not necessarily equal to the stratum-specific OR, i.e. the COR. This statement holds even when W is only related to the outcome, and not the intervention, and is thus not a confounder.[2,3] In fact, it is even possible that the conditional odds ratio shows a benefit of the intervention in every stratum, but no benefit overall, i.e. marginally. This case is known as Simpson’s paradox. We encourage the reader to read the below references 2 and 3 plus Judea Pearls&amp;rsquo; new book, &lt;strong&gt;The Book of Why&lt;/strong&gt; for more insights. Please note that while the odds ratio is non-collapsible, other measures of association like the risk-difference and the risk ratios are collapsible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Multivariable regression versus the G-Formula&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To identify the MOR, classical epidemiologic methods, such as standard multivariable logistic regression models, where the treatment is included as a covariate in the analysis, require the assumption that the effect measure of the treatment of interest is constant across the levels of confounders included in the model.[4] However, in observational studies evaluating the effect of public health interventions, this is often not the case (i.e. the effect of the intervention might differ across individuals with different susceptibilities or characteristics). This is essentially the first point we made in the paragraph above. The second point says that certain effect measures, like the odds ratio, suffer from non-collapsibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, in summary, as pointed out by Spiegelman et al [1] it can a be an option to use regression models to adjust for confounding; but we need to assume  no effect modification and we need to choose  a measure that is collapsible, like the &lt;strong&gt;risk difference&lt;/strong&gt;, rather than the odds ratio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An alternative to using multivariable regression adjustment is the &lt;strong&gt;G-Formula&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;a generalization of standardization with respect to the confounder distribution&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;. In 1986, a seminal paper [5] demonstrated that under assumptions (conditional exchangeability, positivity, consistency, and non-interference, see Appendix below), a consistent estimate of the MOR can be obtained using the G-formula. G-computation,[6] based on the estimation of the components in the G-formula, allows for a treatment effect that may vary across the levels of the confounders.  Furthermore, under the assumption that the DAG above (Figure 1) is correct and the other assumptions, we can estimate the MOR using the g-formula as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;MOR.png&#34; alt=&#34;Figure Link&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where P(W=w) refers to the marginal probability of w.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Monte-Carlo simulation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We implement a Monte Carlo simulation based on the above population-based cancer epidemiology scenario and provide the R code for replication in this GitHub repository: (&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/migariane/hetmor/blob/master/MonteCarloSimulation.r&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;R script for simulation&lt;/a&gt;). As noted above, we are interested in how different the risk of death would have been had everyone received dual therapy compared to if everyone had experienced monotherapy. This is a relevant research question that, answered at a population level, may have an important public health implications for cancer patients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data generating process&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We used the R-package simcausal [7] to generate data according to the DAG introduced above.  The data are (W= (W1, W2, W3, W4), A, Y) where w1 refers to age, W2 to socioeconomic status, W3 to comorbidities, and W4 to cancer stage. The detailed setup can be found here (&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/migariane/hetmor/blob/master/MonteCarloSimulation.r&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;R script for simulation&lt;/a&gt;). In the outcome model, we included an interaction term between treatment A and both comorbidities (W2) and cancer stage (W4), based on the plausible biological mechanism that there is an increased risk of comorbidities among older adults and a different treatment effect for those patients with and without comorbidities and advanced cancer stage. The simulation is based on a sample size of 5000, and 10.000 simulation runs. We estimate the bias with respect to the MOR. Figure 2 shows the results of the above described Monte Carlo simulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 2&lt;/strong&gt; Absolute bias with respect the marginal causal odds ratio comparing the conditional odds ratio from classical multivariable logistic regression models versus the marginal odds ratio from G-computation based on the G-Formula, n = 5,000 and 10,000 simulation runs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;Figure2.png&#34; alt=&#34;Figure Link&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Briefly, one can see the bias of the multivariable logistic regression model is more pronounced under effect modification but persists -due to non-collapsibility- even under no effect modification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;acknowledgements&#34;&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MALF is supported by the Spanish National Institute of Health Carlos III Miguel Servet I Investigator Award (CP17/00206)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;figure-legends&#34;&gt;Figure legends&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 1&lt;/strong&gt;. Directed Acyclic Graph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 2&lt;/strong&gt;. Results from the simulation described on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/migariane/hetmor&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://github.com/migariane/hetmor&lt;/a&gt;. One wants to compare the mortality risk after 1 year of patients with dual therapy (radio- and chemotherapy) with patients on dual therapy (chemotherapy only). Known confounders are age, socioeconomic status, comorbidities, and clinical stage. The absolute bias with respect to the marginal causal odds ratio is reported, based on a sample size of 5000, and 10.000 simulation runs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;appendix&#34;&gt;Appendix&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to be able to consistently estimate the MOR, the data must satisfy the following assumptions [8]: i) Cancer treatment is independent of the potential mortality outcomes (Y(0), Y(1)) after conditioning on W. This assumption is often referred to as “conditional exchangeability” and one cannot test it using the observed data. It implies that (within the strata of W) the mortality risk under the potential treatment A=1, i.e. P(Y(1)=1|A=1,W) equals the one under treatment A=0, i.e. P(Y(1)=1|A=0,W). In other words: the risk of death for those treated would have been the same as for those untreated if untreated subjects had received, contrary to the fact, the treatment. This is equivalent to assuming that all confounders have been measured. ii) We also assume that within strata of W every patient had a nonzero probability of receiving either of the two treatment conditions, i.e. 0 &amp;lt;P(A=1|W)&amp;lt;1 (positivity). iii) We assume consistency, which states that we observe the potential outcome corresponding with the observed treatment, i.e. for any individual, Y = AY(1) + (1 – A)Y(0). Also, iv) in defining an individual’s counterfactual outcome as only a function of their own treatment, we assume non-interference, meaning that the counterfactual outcome of one subject was not influenced by the treatment of any other. Thus, if we believe these assumptions to hold and the sample size to be sufficient, we may interpret our estimate of the MOR approximately as the marginal causal riks of one-year mortality for cancer patients treated with monotherapy versus dual therapy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;thank-you&#34;&gt;Thank you&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for reading through this epidemiological material.&lt;br /&gt;
If you have updates or changes that you would like to make, please send &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/migariane/hetmor&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;me&lt;/a&gt; a pull request.
Alternatively, if you have any questions, please e-mail us at miguel-angel.luque at lshtm.ac.uk&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;strong&gt;cite&lt;/strong&gt; this repository as:&lt;br /&gt;
Luque-Fernandez MA, Daniel Redondo Sanchez, Michael Schomaker (2018). Effect modification and collapsibility when estimating the effect of interventions: A Monte Carlo Simulation comparing classical multivariable regression adjustment versus the G-Formula based on a cancer epidemiology illustration. GitHub repository, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/migariane/hetmor&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://github.com/migariane/hetmor&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Twitter&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;code&gt;@WATZILEI&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spiegelman D, Zhou X. Evaluating Public Health Interventions: 8. Causal Inference for Time-Invariant Interventions. Am J Public Health. 2018:e1-e4.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Greenland S, Robins JM, Pearl J. Confounding and collapsibility in causal inference. Statistical Science. 1999;14(1):29-46.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sjolander A, Dahlqwist E, Zetterqvist J. A Note on the Noncollapsibility of Rate Differences and Rate Ratios. Epidemiology. 2016;27(3):356-359.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keil AP, Edwards JK, Richardson DB, Naimi AI, Cole SR. The parametric g-formula for time-to-event data: intuition and a worked example. Epidemiology. 2014;25(6):889-897.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Greenland S, Robins JM. Identifiability, exchangeability, and epidemiological confounding. International journal of epidemiology. 1986;15(3):413&amp;ndash;419&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Snowden JM, Rose S, Mortimer KM. Implementation of G-computation on a simulated data set: demonstration of a causal inference technique. Am J Epidemiol. 2011;173(7):731-738.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sofrygin O, van der Laan MJ, Neugebauer R (2015). simcausal: Simulating Longitudinal Data with Causal Inference Applications. R package version 0.5.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Luque Fernandez MA, Schomaker M, Rachet B, Schnitzer ME. Targeted maximum likelihood estimation for a binary treatment: A tutorial. Stat Med. 2018;37:2530-2546.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Colliders in Epidemiology: an educational interactive web application</title>
      <link>https://maluque.netlify.com/project/collider/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maluque.netlify.com/project/collider/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Correlation is not causation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
During the last 30 years, classical epidemiology has focussed on the control of confounding [1]. However, it is only recently that epidemiologists have started to focus on the bias produced by colliders and mediators in addition to confounders [2, 3]. In the epidemiological literature different explanations have been proposed to describe the paradoxical protective effect of established risk factors. Such as, for example, the protective effect of maternal smoking on infant mortality and the incidence of pre-eclampsia, namely the birth weight and the smoking pre-eclampsia paradoxes [4, 5].&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;What is a collider?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
A collider for a certain pair of variables (outcome and exposure) is a third variable that is influenced by both of them. Controlling for, or conditioning the analysis on (i.e., stratification or regression) a collider, can introduce a spurious association between its causes (exposure and outcome) potentially explaining why the medical literature is full of paradoxical findings [6]. In DAG terminology, a collider is the variable in the middle of an inverted fork (i.e., variable W in A -&amp;gt; W &amp;lt;- Y) [7]. While this methodological note will not close the vexing gap between correlation and causation, but it will contribute to the increasing awareness and the general understanding of colliders among applied epidemiologists and medical researchers.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Objective&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
To illustrate with an educational purpose the effect of conditioning on a collider based on a realistic non-communicable disease epidemiology example (hypertension and dietary sodium intake). We estimate the effect of 24-hour dietary sodium intake in grams (exposure) on systolic blood pressure (outcome) accounting for the effect of age (confounder). The objective of the illustration is to show the paradoxical effect of 24-hour dietary sodium intake on systolic blood pressure after conditioning on 24-hour excretion of urinary protein (collider).&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Link to the web application&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://watzilei.com/shiny/collider/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://watzilei.com/shiny/collider/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[1] Sander Greenland and Hal Morgenstern. Confounding in health research. Annual Review of Public Health, 22(1):189-212, May 2001.&lt;br /&gt;
[2] Stephen R Cole, RobertWPlatt, Enrique F Schisterman, Haitao Chu, Daniel Westreich, David Richardson, and Charles Poole. Illustrating bias due to conditioning on a collider. International Journal of Epidemiology, 39(2):417-420, Nov 2009.&lt;br /&gt;
[3] Tyler J. Vanderweele and Stijn Vansteelandt. Conceptual issues concerning mediation, interventions and composition. Statistics and Its Interface, 2(4):457-468, 2009.&lt;br /&gt;
[4] Miguel Angel Luque-Fernandez, Helga Zoega, Unnur Valdimarsdottir, and Michelle A. Williams. Deconstructing the smoking-preeclampsia paradox through a counterfactual framework. European Journal of Epidemiology, 31(6):613-623, Jun 2016.&lt;br /&gt;
[5] S. Hernandez-Diaz, E. F. Schisterman, and M. A. Hernan. The birth weight &amp;ldquo;paradox&amp;rdquo; uncovered? American Journal of Epidemiology, 164(11):1115-1120, Sep 2006.&lt;br /&gt;
[6] Julia M Rohrer. Thinking clearly about correlations and causation: Graphical causal models for observational data. 2017.&lt;br /&gt;
[7] Judea Pearl. Causal diagrams for empirical research. Biometrika, 82(4):669-688, 1995.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Targeted Maximum Likelihood Estimation: A tutorial</title>
      <link>https://maluque.netlify.com/publication/sim/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maluque.netlify.com/publication/sim/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;KEYWORDS: Causal Inference, Machine Learning, Observational Studies, Targeted Maximum Likelihood Estimation, Super Learner, Epidemiology, Statistics&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data-Adaptive Estimation for Double-Robust Methods in Population-Based Cancer Epidemiology: Risk differences for lung cancer mortality by emergency presentation</title>
      <link>https://maluque.netlify.com/publication/tmle/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maluque.netlify.com/publication/tmle/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Clinical Epidemiology in the Era of the Big Data Revolution: New Opportunities.</title>
      <link>https://maluque.netlify.com/talk/example-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maluque.netlify.com/talk/example-talk/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ensemble Learning Targeted Maximum Likelihood Estimation, at London.</title>
      <link>https://maluque.netlify.com/talk/example-talk2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maluque.netlify.com/talk/example-talk2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Embed your slides or video here using &lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/post/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;shortcodes&lt;/a&gt;. Further details can easily be added using &lt;em&gt;Markdown&lt;/em&gt; and $\rm \LaTeX$ math code.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ensemble Learning for Model Prediction in Cancer Epidemiology</title>
      <link>https://maluque.netlify.com/project/elmpce/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maluque.netlify.com/project/elmpce/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am developing a cutting edge approach to evaluate and calibrate the performance of new and classic cancer comorbodity index such as the Charlson&amp;rsquo;s comorbidity score. Using a logistic model impose stringent constraints on the association between the explanatory variables and risk of death. For instance, the main-term logistic regression typically relies on a linear and additive relationship between a pre-specified transformation of the mean outcome and its predictors. Given the complex relationship between cancer mortality and comorbidity, the predictive power might be low if an incorrect parametric model is used as opposed to a more flexible option. I am using Data adaptive ensemble learning methods based on the Super Learner as a method for variable selection via cross-validation to select the optimum regression algorithm among all weighted combinations of a set of candidate machine learning algorithms. I am using different machine learning algorithms (Generalized Linear Models, Regression Trees, Bayesian Additive Regression Trees, Gradient Boosting, Generalized Additive Models, Stepwise Regression, Bayesian GLM, Lasso regression, Ridge Regression, Random Forest, Polynomial Spline Regression, and Bagging Classifier Trees). Then using cross-validation techniques I split the data into the mutually exclusive and exhaustive blocks of roughly equal size. Each algorithm is then fitted with nine blocks (the training set) and used to predict mortality for patients in the remaining block (the validation set). Finally, I calculate the mean squared error (MSE) between predicted and recorded mortality outcome comparing classical methods for prediction, machine learning and ensemble learning techniques.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Targeted Maximum Likelihood Estimation: A Tutorial for Applied Researchers</title>
      <link>https://maluque.netlify.com/project/tmle/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maluque.netlify.com/project/tmle/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When estimating the average treatment effect for a binary or continuous outcome, methods that incorporate propensity scores, the G-formula, or Targeted Maximum Likelihood Estimation (TMLE) are preferred over naïve regression approaches which often lead misspecified models. Some methods require correct specification of the outcome model, whereas other methods require correct specification of the exposure model. Doubly-robust methods only require correct specification of one of these models. TMLE is a semiparametric doubly-robust method that enhances correct model specification by allowing flexible estimation using non-parametric machine-learning methods and requires weaker assumptions than its competitors. We provide a step-by-step guided implementation of TMLE and illustrate it in a realistic scenario based on cancer epidemiology where assumptions about correct model specification and positivity (i.e., when a study participant had zero probability of receiving the treatment) are nearly violated. This tutorial (&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/migariane/MALF&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://github.com/migariane/MALF&lt;/a&gt;) provides a concise and reproducible educational introduction to TMLE for a binary outcome and exposure. The reader should gain sufficient understanding of TMLE from this introductory tutorial to be able to apply the method in practice. Extensive R-code is provided in easy-to-read boxes throughout the article for replicability. Stata users will find a testing implementation of TMLE and additional material in the appendix and at the following GitHub repository: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/migariane/SIM-TMLE-tutorial&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://github.com/migariane/SIM-TMLE-tutorial&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>cvAUROC</title>
      <link>https://maluque.netlify.com/project/cvauroc/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maluque.netlify.com/project/cvauroc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Receiver operating characteristic (ROC) analysis is used for comparing predictive models, both in model selection and model evaluation. This method is often applied in clinical medicine and social science to assess the tradeoff between model sensitivity and specificity. After fitting a binary logistic regression model with a set of independent variables, the predictive performance of this set of variables -as assessed by the area under the curve (AUC) from a ROC curve- must be estimated for a sample (the test sample) that is independent of the sample used to predict the dependent variable (the training sample). An important aspect of predictive modeling (regardless of model type) is the ability of a model to generalize to new cases. Evaluating the predictive performance (AUC) of a set of independent variables using all cases from the original analysis sample tends to result in an overly optimistic estimate of predictive performance. K-fold cross-validation can be used to generate a more realistic estimate of predictive performance. To assess this ability in situations in which the number of observations is not very large, cross-validation and bootstrap strategies are useful. cvAUROC implements is a Stata program that implements k-fold cross-validation for the AUC for a binary outcome after fitting a logistic regression model.&lt;br /&gt;
1. &lt;a href=&#34;https://ideas.repec.org/c/boc/bocode/s458324.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://ideas.repec.org/c/boc/bocode/s458324.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
2. &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/migariane/cvAUROC&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://github.com/migariane/cvAUROC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deconstructing the smoking-preeclampsia paradox through a counterfactual framework</title>
      <link>https://maluque.netlify.com/publication/psp/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maluque.netlify.com/publication/psp/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
