<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>MALF on MALF</title>
    <link>https://maluque.netlify.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content in MALF on MALF</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Miguel Angel Luque Fernandez</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Colliders in Epidemiology: an educational interactive web application</title>
      <link>https://maluque.netlify.com/project/collider/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maluque.netlify.com/project/collider/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Correlation is not causation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
During the last 30 years, classical epidemiology has focussed on the control of confounding [1]. However, it is only recently that epidemiologists have started to focus on the bias produced by colliders and mediators in addition to confounders [2, 3]. In the epidemiological literature different explanations have been proposed to describe the paradoxical protective effect of established risk factors. Such as, for example, the protective effect of maternal smoking on infant mortality and the incidence of pre-eclampsia, namely the birth weight and the smoking pre-eclampsia paradoxes [4, 5].&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;What is a collider?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
A collider for a certain pair of variables (outcome and exposure) is a third variable that is influenced by both of them. Controlling for, or conditioning the analysis on (i.e., stratification or regression) a collider, can introduce a spurious association between its causes (exposure and outcome) potentially explaining why the medical literature is full of paradoxical findings [6]. In DAG terminology, a collider is the variable in the middle of an inverted fork (i.e., variable W in A -&amp;gt; W &amp;lt;- Y) [7]. While this methodological note will not close the vexing gap between correlation and causation, but it will contribute to the increasing awareness and the general understanding of colliders among applied epidemiologists and medical researchers.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Objective&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
To illustrate with an educational purpose the effect of conditioning on a collider based on a realistic non-communicable disease epidemiology example (hypertension and dietary sodium intake). We estimate the effect of 24-hour dietary sodium intake in grams (exposure) on systolic blood pressure (outcome) accounting for the effect of age (confounder). The objective of the illustration is to show the paradoxical effect of 24-hour dietary sodium intake on systolic blood pressure after conditioning on 24-hour excretion of urinary protein (collider).&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Link to the web application&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://watzilei.com/shiny/collider/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://watzilei.com/shiny/collider/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[1] Sander Greenland and Hal Morgenstern. Confounding in health research. Annual Review of Public Health, 22(1):189-212, May 2001.&lt;br /&gt;
[2] Stephen R Cole, RobertWPlatt, Enrique F Schisterman, Haitao Chu, Daniel Westreich, David Richardson, and Charles Poole. Illustrating bias due to conditioning on a collider. International Journal of Epidemiology, 39(2):417-420, Nov 2009.&lt;br /&gt;
[3] Tyler J. Vanderweele and Stijn Vansteelandt. Conceptual issues concerning mediation, interventions and composition. Statistics and Its Interface, 2(4):457-468, 2009.&lt;br /&gt;
[4] Miguel Angel Luque-Fernandez, Helga Zoega, Unnur Valdimarsdottir, and Michelle A. Williams. Deconstructing the smoking-preeclampsia paradox through a counterfactual framework. European Journal of Epidemiology, 31(6):613-623, Jun 2016.&lt;br /&gt;
[5] S. Hernandez-Diaz, E. F. Schisterman, and M. A. Hernan. The birth weight &amp;ldquo;paradox&amp;rdquo; uncovered? American Journal of Epidemiology, 164(11):1115-1120, Sep 2006.&lt;br /&gt;
[6] Julia M Rohrer. Thinking clearly about correlations and causation: Graphical causal models for observational data. 2017.&lt;br /&gt;
[7] Judea Pearl. Causal diagrams for empirical research. Biometrika, 82(4):669-688, 1995.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Targeted Maximum Likelihood Estimation: A tutorial</title>
      <link>https://maluque.netlify.com/publication/sim/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maluque.netlify.com/publication/sim/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;KEYWORDS: Causal Inference, Machine Learning, Observational Studies, Targeted Maximum Likelihood Estimation, Super Learner, Epidemiology, Statistics&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data-Adaptive Estimation for Double-Robust Methods in Population-Based Cancer Epidemiology: Risk differences for lung cancer mortality by emergency presentation</title>
      <link>https://maluque.netlify.com/publication/tmle/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maluque.netlify.com/publication/tmle/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Clinical Epidemiology in the Era of the Big Data Revolution: New Opportunities.</title>
      <link>https://maluque.netlify.com/talk/example-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maluque.netlify.com/talk/example-talk/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ensemble Learning Targeted Maximum Likelihood Estimation, at London.</title>
      <link>https://maluque.netlify.com/talk/example-talk2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maluque.netlify.com/talk/example-talk2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Embed your slides or video here using &lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/post/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;shortcodes&lt;/a&gt;. Further details can easily be added using &lt;em&gt;Markdown&lt;/em&gt; and $\rm \LaTeX$ math code.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ensemble Learning for Model Prediction in Cancer Epidemiology</title>
      <link>https://maluque.netlify.com/project/elmpce/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maluque.netlify.com/project/elmpce/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am developing a cutting edge approach to evaluate and calibrate the performance of new and classic cancer comorbodity index such as the Charlson&amp;rsquo;s comorbidity score. Using a logistic model impose stringent constraints on the association between the explanatory variables and risk of death. For instance, the main-term logistic regression typically relies on a linear and additive relationship between a pre-specified transformation of the mean outcome and its predictors. Given the complex relationship between cancer mortality and comorbidity, the predictive power might be low if an incorrect parametric model is used as opposed to a more flexible option. I am using Data adaptive ensemble learning methods based on the Super Learner as a method for variable selection via cross-validation to select the optimum regression algorithm among all weighted combinations of a set of candidate machine learning algorithms. I am using different machine learning algorithms (Generalized Linear Models, Regression Trees, Bayesian Additive Regression Trees, Gradient Boosting, Generalized Additive Models, Stepwise Regression, Bayesian GLM, Lasso regression, Ridge Regression, Random Forest, Polynomial Spline Regression, and Bagging Classifier Trees). Then using cross-validation techniques I split the data into the mutually exclusive and exhaustive blocks of roughly equal size. Each algorithm is then fitted with nine blocks (the training set) and used to predict mortality for patients in the remaining block (the validation set). Finally, I calculate the mean squared error (MSE) between predicted and recorded mortality outcome comparing classical methods for prediction, machine learning and ensemble learning techniques.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Targeted Maximum Likelihood Estimation: A Tutorial for Applied Researchers</title>
      <link>https://maluque.netlify.com/project/tmle/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maluque.netlify.com/project/tmle/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When estimating the average treatment effect for a binary or continuous outcome, methods that incorporate propensity scores, the G-formula, or Targeted Maximum Likelihood Estimation (TMLE) are preferred over naïve regression approaches which often lead misspecified models. Some methods require correct specification of the outcome model, whereas other methods require correct specification of the exposure model. Doubly-robust methods only require correct specification of one of these models. TMLE is a semiparametric doubly-robust method that enhances correct model specification by allowing flexible estimation using non-parametric machine-learning methods and requires weaker assumptions than its competitors. We provide a step-by-step guided implementation of TMLE and illustrate it in a realistic scenario based on cancer epidemiology where assumptions about correct model specification and positivity (i.e., when a study participant had zero probability of receiving the treatment) are nearly violated. This tutorial (&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/migariane/MALF&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://github.com/migariane/MALF&lt;/a&gt;) provides a concise and reproducible educational introduction to TMLE for a binary outcome and exposure. The reader should gain sufficient understanding of TMLE from this introductory tutorial to be able to apply the method in practice. Extensive R-code is provided in easy-to-read boxes throughout the article for replicability. Stata users will find a testing implementation of TMLE and additional material in the appendix and at the following GitHub repository: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/migariane/SIM-TMLE-tutorial&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://github.com/migariane/SIM-TMLE-tutorial&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>cvAUROC</title>
      <link>https://maluque.netlify.com/project/cvauroc/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maluque.netlify.com/project/cvauroc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Receiver operating characteristic (ROC) analysis is used for comparing predictive models, both in model selection and model evaluation. This method is often applied in clinical medicine and social science to assess the tradeoff between model sensitivity and specificity. After fitting a binary logistic regression model with a set of independent variables, the predictive performance of this set of variables -as assessed by the area under the curve (AUC) from a ROC curve- must be estimated for a sample (the test sample) that is independent of the sample used to predict the dependent variable (the training sample). An important aspect of predictive modeling (regardless of model type) is the ability of a model to generalize to new cases. Evaluating the predictive performance (AUC) of a set of independent variables using all cases from the original analysis sample tends to result in an overly optimistic estimate of predictive performance. K-fold cross-validation can be used to generate a more realistic estimate of predictive performance. To assess this ability in situations in which the number of observations is not very large, cross-validation and bootstrap strategies are useful. cvAUROC implements is a Stata program that implements k-fold cross-validation for the AUC for a binary outcome after fitting a logistic regression model.&lt;br /&gt;
1. &lt;a href=&#34;https://ideas.repec.org/c/boc/bocode/s458324.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://ideas.repec.org/c/boc/bocode/s458324.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
2. &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/migariane/cvAUROC&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://github.com/migariane/cvAUROC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deconstructing the smoking-preeclampsia paradox through a counterfactual framework</title>
      <link>https://maluque.netlify.com/publication/psp/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maluque.netlify.com/publication/psp/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
